Well hi there everybody.
안녕하세요, 여러분
I'm not going to give you my usual song and dance about how excited you are, because I know how excited
얼마나 신났는지 평소처럼 말하진 않을게요 저도 그렇고 당신도
you are, as am I.
신났으니까요
No doubt overnight your run has been running as mine has, and you are eager to see the results.
밤새도록 저처럼 달리셨을 테니 결과를 빨리 보고 싶으시겠죠
But we have some content to do.
하지만 할 일이 있어요
First of all, um, so already you can do so many things, uh, coding against frontier and open source
우선, 이미 많은 것을 할 수 있습니다 프론티어에 반하는 코딩과 오픈 소스 모델은
models using data set curation, baseline and fine tuning, frontier models, and now running.
데이터 세트 큐레이션, 기준선 미세 튜닝 프론티어 모델과 실행을 이용하죠
Q Laura, uh, so today I had previously said they were going to be two bullets, but I have put in
Q 로라, 아까 총알 두 개를 넣겠다고 했는데 여기 하나 더
an extra bullet here, beginning here with how training works.
넣었어요 훈련 과정부터 시작하죠 Put
It occurs to me that I've been quite hand-wavy about the training process itself.
생각해보니 훈련 과정 자체에 대해 꽤 꼼꼼하게 알고 있었어요
And at this point, now that you've got some hands on experience running, training, seeing Laura in
이제 여러분은 달리기와 훈련 로라의 활약을 직접 목격한 경험이
action, it's worth me just taking a minute to explain it properly.
있으니 잠시 시간을 내서 제대로 설명해 드릴게요
So you've got that basis.
그런 기본이 있어요
You may know it all already.
이미 다 알고 계실지도 몰라요
It might be something that at this point you've either picked up or you already had had encountered.
그 시점에서 뭔가 알아차렸거나 이미 마주쳤을 수도 있죠
Um, either way, I think it's super important that I do clarify that.
어느 쪽이든 그걸 분명히 하는 게 중요해요
And so we'll take a couple of minutes to do it.
몇 분 정도 걸릴 거예요
Um, and I think it's really nice that you've had some experience first running training so that this
첫 달리기 훈련을 받은 건 좋은 일이라고 생각해요 이번
will hopefully connect the dots and things will click in place.
훈련을 통해 모든 게 잘 연결되길 바라요
We will then run inference for a fine tuned model, and then we will have the conclusion of week seven,
그런 다음 잘 조율된 모델에 대한 추론을 실행합니다 그럼 7주 차에 마무리되는 거죠 정말
which is exciting indeed.
흥미진진해요
All right let's get started.
Get it, get it, get it, get it, get, it! 자, 그럼 시작해 볼까요?
So I want to explain that the training process, the process of improving a model so that it's better
제가 말씀드리고 싶은 것은 모델을 개선하는 훈련 과정으로 작업을 수행하는
and better at performing a task, is something that has four steps to it.
데 있어서 4단계를 거쳐야 한다는 점인데요
The first step is what's known as the forward pass, which is just another name for a sort of running
첫 단계는 전진 패스라고 알려진 겁니다 일종의 실행 추론에 쓰이는 또 다른
inference.
이름이죠
You have a data, a point in your data set, you have a particular training data point, and you take
데이터 집합에 데이터가 있는데 특정 훈련 데이터 포인트가 있고 그 훈련 프롬프트를
that that training prompt and you pass it through your neural network to get the prediction for the
신경망을 통해 전달해 다음 토큰에 대한 예측을 얻죠.
And that is called the forward pass, because you're thinking of the input coming in, going through,
그걸 포워드 패스라고 하죠 왜냐하면 입력값이 들어와 통과하고
and the output popping out at the end of your transformer.
결과물이 변압기 끝에 튀어나온다고 생각하니까요
There is then what's called the loss calculation.
그리고 손실 계산이라는 게 있어요
And we'll talk a little bit more about this later.
이 비트에 대해선 나중에 더 얘기하죠
But this is saying okay.
이건 괜찮다고 하네요
So the network predicted that this would be the output.
네트워크는 이게 출력물이라고 예상했어요
And in fact this is the true next token because we're in training.
사실 이게 진정한 다음 토큰이에요 우린 훈련 중이니까요
And so we've got real examples that include what actually did come next in the data.
데이터에서 다음에 무엇이 올지 포함하는 실제 예제들이 있어요
And so now that you've got the prediction and the truth, you can come come up with some way of calculating
이제 예측과 진실을 알았으니 손실을 계산할 방법을 생각해낼 수 있겠죠
the loss or how wrong were you.
얼마나 틀렸는지도 알고요
How bad was it loss being the sort of inverse of of of accuracy.
정확성의 반대인 걸 잃었을 때 얼마나 심각했나요?
So a bigger loss number means things went worse.
손실이 크다는 건 상황이 악화됐다는 뜻이죠
So that's step two.
이게 2단계예요
The loss calculation.
손실 계산요
Step three is known as the backward pass.
세 번째 단계는 뒤로 가기예요
And you hear different terms for this.
다른 용어도 많이 들리죠
It's called backprop back propagation.
백프롭 백 전파라고 하죠
Um and the idea is that in in this backward pass you take this loss and you look back through the neural
이 원리는 이 역과정에서 손실을 감안하고 신경망을 통해 되돌아보며 이런 질문을
network and you ask the question, if I were to tweak each of the parameters in this neural network
하는 겁니다 신경망의 각 매개 변수를 조금씩만 변경한다면요
Would it have made this loss bigger or smaller?
이 손실이 커졌을까요? 작아졌을까요?
How is the loss dependent?
손실이 얼마나 크죠?
How is this particular weight?
이 무게는 어떻게 정했죠?
Uh, how does that vary the loss?
그게 손실과 무슨 상관이죠?
Um, what's the difference in loss based on on this weight?
몸무게에 따라 감량량은 어떻게 달라지죠?
Um, and that that sensitivity is called a gradient.
그 민감한 부분을 그러데이션이라고 해요
Of course.
물론이죠
Um, as, as, as it is generally in maths.
일반적으로 수학에서 그렇듯이요
Uh, and so this is about calculating the gradients of all of your weights to see how the loss is affected
각 무게의 경사도를 계산하는 과정이에요 조금만 변경해도 손실이 발생하죠
by a small tweak to those weights, so that, that calculating the gradients of all of your weights
그래서 모든 무게의 경사도를 계산하는 과정을 백워드
is known as the backward pass.
패스라고 해요
Uh, and then finally, the fourth step optimization is, uh, and this is the thing that we selected
마지막으로 4단계 최적화는 무게 감쇠 기능을 갖춘 Adam
the Adam with weight decay, the Adam W optimizer for our particular training exercise.
W 최적화기로 훈련에 사용하기로 했어요
Optimization is saying, okay, so now we've calculated all of our gradients.
최적화는 모든 그러데이션을 계산했다는 뜻이에요
What we now want to do is we want to tweak all of the weights a tiny tiny bit such that next time,
이제 모든 무게 비트를 조금씩 조정할 겁니다 그래야 다음번에
if it were given the same prompt, it would be more likely to do a little bit better.
같은 프롬프트를 받으면 좀 더 잘 되겠죠
The loss would be a little bit lower.
비트 박스는 좀 낮겠죠
So we're going to tweak in the in the direction the opposite direction to the to the gradient so that
기울기 방향과 반대 방향으로 살짝 조정해서 손실을
losses would be reduced.
줄일 거예요
And that small step which is based on the learning rate, how much of a step you take is based on on
학습 비율에 따라 한 단계씩 나아가는 겁니다 학습 비율이 얼마나 큰지에
how big the learning rate is, is designed to make things a little bit better.
따라서요 이건 좀 더 나은 환경을 위해 고안된 거죠
And you always want to try and do it in a way that will generalize well.
일반화할 수 있는 방법으로 항상 시도하고 싶죠
You don't want to just be solving for exactly this input prompt.
이 입력 프롬프트를 정확히 해결하고 싶진 않죠
You just want the model to be learning to get a little bit better with those kinds of prompts in the
이런 비트로 모델이 좀 더 나아지도록 배우길 바랄 뿐이죠
Um, and of course, all of this process happens with mini batches at the same time, and it happens
이 모든 과정이 미니 배치에서 동시에 발생합니다 데이터 전체에서
again and again and again all the way through your your data is one epoch and then potentially another
계속 반복되죠 데이터는 한 발생을 거치고 여러 발생을 거치면서
time and another time after that as it goes through multiple epochs.
또 다른 발생이 반복돼요
So that repeated process is what is known as training.
그 반복적인 과정을 훈련이라고 하죠
And now in the next video, we will just step through a diagram to illustrate that.
다음 비디오에서는 그걸 설명하기 위해 다이어그램을 보여드리죠